Guide to the Terra Research Magazine 2006-2019
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Terra Research Magazine
2006-2019
Oregon State University. News and Research Communications.
PUB 492
0.35 cubic feet 1 box
8.3 Gbytes
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Terra Research Magazine consists of print and born-digital content highlighting the research, scholarship, and creative endeavors of faculty and students at Oregon State University. Terra was launched in spring 2006 with a color print magazine and companion website. Most issues of Terra are available online in Oregon Digital.
Historical Note:
The inaugural issue of the Terra research magazine was issued in spring 2006 with Nicolas Houtman as the founding editor and a goal to highlight the stories, accomplishments, and impacts of Oregon State University researchers. Terra is published three times per year with issues released in the fall, winter, and spring. Summer issues were published in 2006, 2007, 2008, and 2011. A companion website with non-print resources was launched at the same time as the print publication. Nick Houtman served as editor through the Spring 2018 issue. Ian Vorster assumed the role of Editor for the Fall 2018 issue.
Houtman, Nick.; Vorster, Ian.
Oregon State University. University Relations and Marketing.; Oregon State University--Faculty.; Oregon State University--Graduate students.; Oregon State University--Research.; Oregon State University--Students.
Born digital.
College students--Research--Oregon--Corvallis.; Universities and colleges--Research--Oregon.
Colleges and Universities; Science; Technology; Oregon; Corvallis; Electronic Records
This publication was received on distribution by the University Archives until 2011 and since then by the Special Collections and Archives Research Center.
Collection is open for research.
The Special Collections and Archives Research Center's holdings include numerous and extensive collections documenting the research enterprise at Oregon State University. Many faculty papers and most academic unit records include materials pertaining to research, scholarship, and creative activities. The Research Office Records (RG 170) and the Agricultural Experiment Station Records (RG 025) document the administration and oversight of research at Oregon State. Oregon's Agricultural Progress Magazine (PUB 006-22a) reports on agricultural research and its impact on Oregon and the world.
The Terra Research Magazine is arranged in two series: 1. Individual Issues, 2006-2019 and 2. Website, 2017-2019.
The Terra Research Magazine consists of print and born-digital content highlighting the research, scholarship, and creative endeavors of faculty and students at Oregon State University. Terra was launched in spring 2006 with a color print magazine and companion website. This collection includes print and born-digital versions of the magazine as well as captures of the accompanying website. Many articles were written by Editor Nick Houtman and writer Lee Sherman.
The content of the magazine represents the full range of research conducted at Oregon State University and includes science, technology, and engineering; natural resources; agriculture, ecosystems, and the environment; marine sciences and climate; and public health. The magazine includes articles highlighting creative efforts in art, music, theater, and apparel design as well as inter-disciplinary research. The research activities of undergraduate and graduate students are described in many articles. Special issues on marine sciences (Winter 2011 and Spring 2016), Oregon’s climate (Winter 2012), human health (Winter 2015) and an annual report on research (Fall 2013) are included in the collection.
Most issues of Terra are available online in Oregon Digital.
- Individual Issues, 2006-2019; Series 1
  Series 1 consists of 40 individual issues of Terra published from 2006 to 2019. Most of the issues are available in both print and born-digital form online. However, several issues are only available online (noted below) and one issue (Summer 2011) is only available in print form. Beginning with Winter 2016, the issues are only available online in digital form, with the exception of the Winter 2018 issue which is available in both print and digital format. Links to individual issues in Oregon Digital are provided below. Born-digital issues total 0.8 Gbytes of digital content.
  - Spring 2006 (Box-folder 1.01)
    Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Summer 2006 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - Winter 2007
    Only available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2007
  - Summer 2007 (Box-folder 1.03)
    The issue includes an article on the OSU Fermentation Lab. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Winter 2008 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - Spring 2008 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - Summer 2008 (Box-folder 1.04)
    This issue includes articles on youth in detention centers and public transportation access for the disabled. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Winter 2009 (Box-folder 1.04)
    This issue includes an article on languages native to Oregon. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2009 (Box-folder 1.04)
  - Fall 2009 (Box-folder 1.05)
    This issue includes articles on organic farming and solar power. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2010 (Box-folder 1.05)
  - Winter 2010
  - Fall 2010 (Box-folder 1.06)
  - Winter 2011 (Box-folder 1.06)
    Special Issue on Marine Sciences. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2011 (Box-folder 1.06)
  - Summer 2011 (Box-folder 1.07)
    This issue includes an article on online security.
  - Fall 2011 (Box-folder 1.07)
    This issue includes an article on apparel design. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Winter 2012 (Box-folder 1.07)
    Special Issue: Oregon's Climate. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2012 (Box-folder 1.07)
    This issue includes an article on race car design. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Fall 2012 (Box-folder 1.08)
    This issue includes articles on animal research ethics and plankton-inspired art. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Winter 2013 (Box-folder 1.08)
  - Spring 2013 (Box-folder 1.08)
  - Fall 2013 (Box-folder 1.09)
    Special Insert: 2013 Annual Report of Research. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Winter 2014 (Box-folder 1.09)
  - Spring 2014 (Box-folder 1.09)
    This issue includes an article on digital surveillance. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Fall 2014 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Winter 2015 (Box-folder 1.10)
    Special Issue: Human Health. Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Spring 2015 (Box-folder 1.10)
    This issue includes an article on women in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). Available online in Oregon Digital.
  - Fall 2015 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Winter 2016
  - Spring 2016
  - Fall 2016
  - Winter 2017
  - Spring 2017
  - Fall 2017
  - Winter 2018 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Spring 2018
  - Fall 2018
  - Winter 2019
- Website, 2017-2019; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of the Terra website as captured periodically from 2017 to 2019 using Archive-It. The captured site can be viewed here. These captures include online stories and access to print versions of the magazine and total 7.5 Gbytes.